here's an intriguing way to use a
rectangle to find the sum of various
geometric series with ratio
1/2 first let's start with a 1x1 Square
the diagonal length in this square is
the square otk of two by the Pythagorean
theorem so if we draw a line segment to
the midpoint of the square on that
diagonal it has a length ofun of 2 over2
now we can draw a horizontal line back
to the square that has a length of 1/2
but then we can repeat this exact
picture in the upper right corner we
take half of the diagonal line to be 2 4
half of the horizontal line to be 1/4
and we can repeat this process over and
over each time we take half of the
previous diagonal and half of the
previous horizontal along the way each
of these line segments has a length of
size 1/ < tk2 raised to the K where K is
some integer starting at one and going
on forever now the infinite sum
represents a limit so we need to think
of the limiting process in this diagram
in the limiting process we see that the
diagonal and horizontal lines fill in
all the way up to the top right corner
of this square and so the sum of the
lengths of this zigzag diagram represent
our infinite sum but now we perform our
trick we rotate the horizontal line
segments 90° about their end point
filling in the right side of the square
and then we shift the diagonal line
segments over to the main diagonal of
the square filling that entirely as well
and this means that the sum of the
lengths of the zigzag diagram must be
equal to the sum of the side length of
the square plus the diagonal of the
square that means our infinite sum is
equal to 1 + the < TK 2 so from this
diagram we see that the sum where K
ranges from 1 to Infinity of 1K 2 raised
to the K power is equal to 1 + < TK of 2
as a bonus fact we note that the number
1 + the of two is known as the Silver
ratio let's see this process in action
again with a 1/2x one rectangle instead
the diagonal length in this rectangle is
the < TK of 5/2 by the Pythagorean
theorem if we take half of the diagonal
and then Traverse back down to the side
of the rectangle we end up with a length
of < TK 5 4 + 1/4 and now we repeat this
process on the lower one quarter by 1/2
rectangle we scale the diagonal length
by half and the vertical line by half
giving us two line segments that sum to
> of 5 8 + 1/8 and then we repeat this
process again and again each time taking
1/2 of the previous sum of two lengths
once again we are interested in the
infinite sum of the lengths of the
zigzag diagram shown here and that means
we're interested in a limiting process
we can think about this limiting process
geometrically as the zigzag diagram
converging in on the lower left corner
filling in entirely again we can rotate
the vertical pink segments 90° and they
fill in half of the side length of one
we can also shift the blue diagonal line
segments up to the main diagonal of the
rectangle filling in the entire diagonal
and that means that the sum that we're
interested in the infinite sum is the
sum of these two lengths so it's 12 + <
TK 5/ 2 this is a geometric series with
first term < TK 5 4 + 1/4 and ratio 12
and we see from this diagram that the
infinite sum where K ranges from 0 to
Infinity of the < TK of 5 + 1 over 4 * 2
K is 12 + > 5/2 this latter number is
known as the golden
ratio now it's your turn why don't you
try this process on a rectangle with
generic side lengths A and B what
infinite sum do you find the sum of
geometrically using this particular
argument this visual proof is due to
anhel Plaza if you liked this video
check out my playlist on geometric sums
that show other ways to find the sum of
geometric series